You're going to create a USB Composable just like I did use task and to be honest, I would say,
especially when you're first getting used to writing Composables, just move stuff in.
Don't think too hard about like, oh, is this utility? Like, if you have an instinct for
immediately, like, cool, like, do your thing, like, move it into a utility. But otherwise, I mean,
if it's related functionality, that's a good, that's a step in the right direction, right?
You can always keep refactoring later on. And so, I guess I also then give it hint as well. There's
a lot of date time stuff in there that, like formatting dates, that's super repeated in the codebase.
And so, you can make some choices about how you might want to do that. So if you want to practice
creating some utility functions, that is there for you as well.
Our goal for this exercise was to create a USB Composable because if you, because if you haven't
chance to take a look, you might have noticed there is a lot of stuff with the weak happening
in the codebase. Like, it's pretty prolific. And so, you know, I think for this particular
Composable, I think this is a good point to demonstrate something that didn't get to talk about earlier,
which is the fact that Composables, we showed the ability with the used tasks that we were
basically exporting some methods and we were using them. But the important thing to remember
about Composable is that they can have anything in it. So, in other words, they can also have
reactive state. And so, Composables are not only a good way to share methods and functionality,
but also to share state between Components. And it's in a lot of ways, one of the more ideal
ideal ones, which we'll talk about in a bit. So, let's go ahead and I'm just going to look for,
let's see, this looks, let's see, let me see if I can find like, so let's look at the weak
model, maybe, is there like, we're looking for, maybe like, a constweaks? There we go, okay,
see, so look, this week's ref is being used in a lot of different places. And so, what we notice here
is that there's essentially pretty duplicated logic as far as like loading, week error. And then
more importantly, you'll notice here that the fetch weeks here then updates the value of weeks.
And so, to demonstrate actually what I was saying, let's actually make this particular
Composable real straightforward. And so, what I'm going to do is I'm going to cut this out,
I'm going to drop it inside of my use week's Composable, and then we just need to make
sure we import ref from view. And then just to keep the type, we just need to import type
week, and then there you go, there's my autocomplete from the types. And then you just need to export this.
And then, believe it or not, just like this, you've now created this reusable piece of state
that we can now go into each one of these pages, and we can actually just straight up remove them.
And instead of having them there, we can just import weeks from our Composable use week.
And that becomes that. This goes, bye bye. This goes here.
This goes gone. That goes there. That disappears. And then, last one.
So, if you couldn't tell with this particular one, this is one of the reasons why some people
have started getting into auto importing, because my whole screen is full of imports at this point.
And that can be a discussion from another time. But here what we just did is we took this thing
that we know we want to share between six different components. And what's beautiful about the
Composables is that it does not care where your components live in relation to one another.
Right? Props need them to be direct ancestors. Or not even that's right. Prop needs to be direct
children if you do provide inject, then you need to be an ancestor. Like there's a bunch of
caveats with these. But Composables, it just knows where to go and it shares it and it's good.
And so, this was part of earlier at the break. And so, this particular pattern is known.
We'll talk a little bit more about this later, but it's called like a singleton.
Because it's this one file that's being used and shared across multiple files. And that's the
reason why it is, that's why you're able to share a state. And then, so again, just a,
we're kind of priming you for, we will do some exercises on this in a little bit.
But the alternative, right? If you were to do something like generate weeks, right?
And then you exported this and said, and you had like cons weeks, or let's say, just to be clear,
new weeks equals ref week like this. Okay, maybe turn new weeks.
If you run this function in every component, it is going to generate you a new one,
every single time, because it's running that function each time.
These are, this is again, this is like a kind of a sneak peek into what we will be talking about,
which is these are the probably like the two paradigms you have to consider when writing
Composables. Another thing that we do want to mention here as well regarding Composables
is that we, I mentioned, you know, they're call Composables that we prefix them with use.
And we put them in a folder called Composables. But I think what's important to clarify is that
all of that is a chosen convention. View isn't doing anything like auto magically,
that like detects the stuff, and then does some sort of magic compilation or anything.
Now, there are libraries that because they know Composables are pattern, they know that they use
prefixes of things. You can basically point it and say, hey, for all my Composables,
just auto import them so that I don't deal with that. So that's like an example of an auto
magic thing that you could have a plug and do for you. But these are all chosen conventions. You could
very well put this Composable inside of the utils folder. And as assuming you update the path,
it works exactly the same. What makes it a Composable is the fact that you're using a ref here
from view and that you're returning something reactive that will impact the state.
So just so I'm clear. Yes. If you import your weeks into several different components,
they're on screen or on in different routes. Uh-huh. And let's say it was a counter and you
incremented it. Yep. That value would be used everywhere. Correct. You would incremented on one
component or one route and it would be reflected on the next page you visit. Correct.
Assuming you're using router link, because I think if you do a full refresh, that
then you're doing with caching things. And there are actually there's actually pretty easy way around
that, which I can demonstrate later. But yes, to your point, as long as you're not dealing with
like anything being busted, cached-wise, it's essentially like a global store that you can put
anywhere. It's many times as you want. To be clear, I guess I'll do this real quick. This one.
That's like the fundamental premise between them.
Yep. And then also for the sake of also being complete about the exercise, we're going to
just create a quick util to show what that looks like just so you can see the difference.
The last one I mentioned was a date time utils. And so we're just, we're going to, we're not going
to go to the whole code base. I would, that would take a while. We're just going to take something
that I fairly certainly will be useful. And so I think we have like a format date, for example,
there's a bunch of stuff. This format date range, I think date range actually was, if I
went around, I was looking to do a cup base, it was a simplest. So here format date range
pretty standard, you get a start date and then date. And then here, you know, you have,
let's say here exactly, you start date and date, yep, look how ditched ring. So all these are
identical. So it is ripe for refactoring. So let's grab that. And then we'll go to our date time
and then we'll drop that in. Export it. Looks like there's nothing magical about this.
No need to import anything else. And so now that we have that, we can close that. And we can
import it at the top. Do two, two, once I get there. Import. It was format date range. There you go.
Got to love autocomplete. And then there you go. And that is, your utility has now been refactored.
So that's there. That's there. That's good. This does not need to be redefined.
So go all the way to the top. Drop that in. There you go. This does not need to be defined here as well.
Voila. And so just like that, this is a great example of like a date time util.